{
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not part of the component of primary health care?",
      "options": [
        "Education",
        "Immunization",
        "Urban development",
        "Accessibility"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Urban development"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Nigeria Primary health care was adopted in the National Health Policy of what year?",
      "options": ["1960", "1988", "1983", "1991"],
      "correctAnswer": "1988"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1985,……….. Was appointed the minister of health who adopted PHC in 52 Local Government areas,",
      "options": [
        "Professor Olikoye Ransome Kuti",
        "Professor Yemi Osinbajo",
        "Dora Akunyili",
        "Mrs. Kemi Adeosun"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Professor Olikoye Ransome Kuti"
    },
    {
      "question": "Reasons for first aid include the following except;",
      "options": [
        "Risk reduction",
        "Reduced severity of injury",
        "Increased mortality rate",
        "Quick intervention"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Increased mortality rate"
    },
    {
      "question": "Emergency conditions includes the following except;",
      "options": ["Shock", "Bleeding", "Burns", "Headache"],
      "correctAnswer": "Headache"
    },
    {
      "question": "Asphyxia means;",
      "options": [
        "Deficient supply of blood to the body",
        "Deficient supply of oxygen to the body",
        "Deficient supply of nutrient to the body",
        "Deficient supply of vitamins to the body"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Deficient supply of oxygen to the body"
    },
    {
      "question": "A life threatening medical condition of low blood perfusion to body tissue is called",
      "options": ["Asphyxiation", "Shock", "Asthma", "Strangulation"],
      "correctAnswer": "Shock"
    },
    {
      "question": "First degree burns usually affect",
      "options": [
        "Superficial skin layer",
        "Deep lying tissues",
        "Bones",
        "Fatty muscles"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Superficial skin layer"
    },
    {
      "question": "Burns which results in loss of sensitivity and pain is best described as",
      "options": [
        "Zero degree burns",
        "First degree burns",
        "Second degree burns",
        "Third degree burns"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Third degree burns"
    },
    {
      "question": "An immediate and temporary care given to a victim of an accident or sudden illness before the services of a physician is called",
      "options": [
        "Medical care",
        "Primary health care",
        "First aid",
        "Intensive care"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "First aid"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is not advisable when you are controlling bleeding",
      "options": [
        "Applying a direct pressure",
        "Elevate the injured part of the lessen blood flow",
        "Applying tourniquet",
        "Pouring lukewarm water to the site of bleeding"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Applying tourniquet"
    },
    {
      "question": "Signs and symptoms of the fracture are the following except;",
      "options": ["Deformity", "Loss of motion", "Splinting", "Swelling"],
      "correctAnswer": "Splinting"
    },
    {
      "question": "A device to immobilize an injured part of the body is called …………..",
      "options": ["Splinting", "Plaster", "Rope", "Tourniquet"],
      "correctAnswer": "Splinting"
    },
    {
      "question": "The part  of the tongue with the sensitive taste of saltiness and sweetness is",
      "options": ["Tip", "Sides", "Back", "Middle"],
      "correctAnswer": "Tip"
    },
    {
      "question": "Dental caries is a disease condition of",
      "options": ["Dentist", "Tooth", "Tongue", "Buccal cavity"],
      "correctAnswer": "Tooth"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is a risk factor of oral cancer?",
      "options": [
        "Proper oral hygiene",
        "Tobacco use",
        "Good nutrition",
        "Drinking of enough water"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Tobacco use"
    },
    {
      "question": "Pharmacy Technician can help in achieving good oral hygiene by doing all the following except:",
      "options": [
        "Avoiding people with poor oral hygiene",
        "Engaging people by providing oral health education",
        "Promoting positive oral health behavior",
        "Taking leads in mobilizing clients for good oral health behavior"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Avoiding people with poor oral hygiene"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is an emergency drug?",
      "options": ["Adrenaline", "Amoxycillin", "Diclofenac", "Omeprazole"],
      "correctAnswer": "Adrenaline"
    },
    {
      "question": "As a first aider; you are an eye witness to an accident case, which one of the following is wrong?",
      "options": [
        "Call for help",
        "Attend to the unconscious victims before the conscious victims",
        "Attend to the conscious victims before the unconscious victims",
        "Do not panic"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Attend to the unconscious victims before the conscious victims"
    },
    {
      "question": "Cardiopulmonary resuscitation is an example of:",
      "options": [
        "Pulmonary disease",
        "Cardiac disease",
        "Pneumonia disease",
        "Life saving procedures"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Life saving procedures"
    },
    {
      "question": "The brain needs …………. For proper functioning.",
      "options": ["Glucose", "Protein", "Vitamins", "Fat"],
      "correctAnswer": "Glucose"
    },
    {
      "question": "The end product of protein is …………..",
      "options": ["Citric acid", "Amino acid", "Gluconic acid", "Glucose"],
      "correctAnswer": "Amino acid"
    },
    {
      "question": "…………. Is the end product of carbohydrates.",
      "options": ["Glucose", "Galactose", "Lactose", "Sucrose"],
      "correctAnswer": "Glucose"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following is a live vaccine?",
      "options": ["Measles", "Cholera", "Typhoid", "Pertussis"],
      "correctAnswer": "Measles"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of the following is not a type of vaccines.",
      "options": [
        "Live vaccine",
        "Killed vaccine",
        "Non conjugate vaccines",
        "Recombinant vaccines"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Non conjugate vaccines"
    },
    {
      "question": "Most vaccines are stored in cold chain equipment because of the following except;",
      "options": [
        "They are sensitive to high temperature",
        "To remain active and potent",
        "To increase their potency and expiry date",
        "They must be stored at low temperatures"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "To increase their potency and expiry date"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following can be self diagnosed?",
      "options": ["Shock", "Burns", "Asphyxia", "Acute abdomen"],
      "correctAnswer": "Acute abdomen"
    },
    {
      "question": "The provider of counseling on family planning/child spacing methods should be:",
      "options": [
        "Friendly and accommodating",
        "Jovial and flirting",
        "Provide inadequate information on sexual and reproductive health",
        "Ensure confidentiality only when its necessary"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Friendly and accommodating"
    },
    {
      "question": "Advantages of family planning includes all but one of these:",
      "options": [
        "Removes fear of unwanted pregnancy",
        "Promote good health",
        "Allows women to have multiple sexual partners",
        "Gives way for planning of the future"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Allows women to have multiple sexual partners"
    },
    {
      "question": "A burn as a result of hot liquid is called:",
      "options": [
        "Thermal burn",
        "Scald",
        "Radiation burn",
        "Hydrolytic burns"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Scald"
    },
    {
      "question": "Weakness, dizziness, palor, cold sweat and unconsciousness are signs and symptoms",
      "options": [
        "Cardiac arrest",
        "Heart failure",
        "Fainting",
        "Acute asthmatic attack"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Fainting"
    },
    {
      "question": "Some of the features of primary health care in Nigeria health system are the following except;",
      "options": [
        "An element of the health system",
        "Inequity",
        "Sustainability and self reliance",
        "Community participation"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Inequity"
    },
    {
      "question": "Primary health care is essentially aimed at all the following but one;",
      "options": [
        "Health promotion",
        "Disease prevention",
        "Intensive care",
        "Curing disease"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Intensive care"
    },
    {
      "question": "Millennium development goals (MDGs) include the under listed except:",
      "options": [
        "Promote gender inequality and empower women",
        "Reduce child mortality",
        "Combat HIV/AIDS, Malaria and other diseases",
        "Achieve universal primary education"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Promote gender inequality and empower women"
    },
    {
      "question": "All the following are very common health issues among aged/elderly except",
      "options": ["Poverty", "Arthritis", "Eye sight failing", "Diabetes"],
      "correctAnswer": "Poverty"
    },
    {
      "question": "The food requirement of an individual depends among others all these except;",
      "options": ["Age", "Body weight", "Culture", "Sex"],
      "correctAnswer": "Culture"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fat soluble vitamins are all these except",
      "options": ["Vitamin A", "Vitamin B", "Vitamin E", "Vitamin K"],
      "correctAnswer": "Vitamin B"
    },
    {
      "question": "Deficiency of protein overtime in a body can result to",
      "options": ["Scurvy", "Kwashiorkor", "Beri beri", "Ricket"],
      "correctAnswer": "Kwashiorkor"
    },
    {
      "question": "Protection against communicable diseases involves the following except",
      "options": [
        "Consuming raw foods",
        "Safe water supply",
        "Sanitary excreta disposal",
        "Safe food preparation"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Consuming raw foods"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following can be described as high risk pregnancy",
      "options": [
        "Pregnancy of more than 2 years apart",
        "Pregnancy after the age of 35 years",
        "Pregnancy after 2 births",
        "Pregnancy after the age of 20"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Pregnancy after the age of 35 years"
    },
    {
      "question": "A Pharmacy Technician in a basic health centre can take part in the antenatal care by",
      "options": [
        "Taking history of the pregnant women",
        "Advising and educating the pregnant women on routine drug use",
        "Checking vital signs",
        "Involving in delivery taking"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Advising and educating the pregnant women on routine drug use"
    },
    {
      "question": "Routine antenatal examination are all the under listed except;",
      "options": [
        "Blood grouping",
        "Blood pressure measurement",
        "Fundal height evaluation",
        "Weight and height taking"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Weight and height taking"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following is wrong in antenatal clinic visits?",
      "options": [
        "Every four weeks till 28 weeks",
        "Every 2 weeks till 36 weeks",
        "Every week until the commencement of labour",
        "Alternate weeks till 40 weeks"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Alternate weeks till 40 weeks"
    },
    {
      "question": "The period between the third stage of labour and the six weeks postpartum is called……",
      "options": ["Post natal care", "Mother care", "Puerperium", "Child care"],
      "correctAnswer": "Puerperium"
    },
    {
      "question": "Routine drugs commonly given to pregnant women during antenatal visits include all but one;",
      "options": ["Ferous", "Folic acid", "Ascorbic acid", "Diclofenac"],
      "correctAnswer": "Diclofenac"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is odd in high risk pregnancies",
      "options": [
        "Balanced diet",
        "Exercise",
        "Sexual activity",
        "Medications"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Sexual activity"
    },
    {
      "question": "Skilled attendants at birth by WHO Standards are all these except;",
      "options": ["TBAs", "Midwives", "Nurses", "Doctors"],
      "correctAnswer": "TBAs"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of these family planning is considered unsafe?",
      "options": [
        "IUCD",
        "Injectable contraceptives",
        "Implant",
        "Withdrawal method"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Withdrawal method"
    },
    {
      "question": "The total or partial removal of the external female genitalia is called……..",
      "options": [
        "Female genital mutilation",
        "Female contraceptive",
        "Sexual assault",
        "Female sexual culture"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Female genital mutilation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Fetus develops and grows until delivery inside",
      "options": ["The oviduct", "The cervix", "The uterus", "The vaginal"],
      "correctAnswer": "The uterus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Some of the wrong reasons for female genital mutilation include all but one",
      "options": [
        "Increases female sexual desires",
        "Curtail female sexual desire",
        "Part of cultural heritage",
        "Aesthetic reasons"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Increases female sexual desires"
    },
    {
      "question": "Vaccines exist for the following diseases except;",
      "options": ["Whooping cough", "Measles", "Snake bites", "Yellow fever"],
      "correctAnswer": "Snake bites"
    },
    {
      "question": "Immunoglobullins include all these except;",
      "options": ["IgP", "IgM", "IgB", "IgE"],
      "correctAnswer": "IgB"
    },
    {
      "question": "The tier of government that is directly responsible for the PHC in Nigeria is",
      "options": [
        "Federal government",
        "State government",
        "Local government",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Local government"
    },
    {
      "question": "Most Tertiary health care facilities are under the control of",
      "options": [
        "State government",
        "Federal government",
        "Local government",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Federal government"
    },
    {
      "question": "General hospitals are;",
      "options": [
        "Tertiary health care",
        "Primary health care",
        "Secondary health care",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Secondary health care"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ‘3Bs’ order of priority when treating accident victims are;",
      "options": [
        "Breathing, bloating, bleeding",
        "Breathing, bleeding, bones",
        "Breathing, bladder, blockade",
        "Breathing, bleeding, blabbing"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Breathing, bleeding, bones"
    },
    {
      "question": "A brief loss of consciousness that is caused by temporary reduction of blood flow to the brain is called………..",
      "options": ["Shock", "Fainting", "Hyperventilation", "Dehydration"],
      "correctAnswer": "Fainting"
    },
    {
      "question": "…………………….. Is the mechanical obstruction of the flow of air from the environment to the lungs",
      "options": ["Choking", "Asthma", "COPD", "Respiratory infections"],
      "correctAnswer": "Choking"
    },
    {
      "question": "……………….is the placement of one or more bones at a joint",
      "options": ["Fracture", "Dislocation", "Bruises", "Sprain"],
      "correctAnswer": "Dislocation"
    },
    {
      "question": "Tourniquet is used in first aid primarily for",
      "options": [
        "Aesthetic purposes",
        "Splinting and bleeding wounds",
        "To set infusion lines",
        "To help carrying a patient to the hospital"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Splinting and bleeding wounds"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following drugs is not an antimalarial",
      "options": [
        "Artesunate",
        "Amoxycillin",
        "Quinine",
        "Arthemether/lumefantrin"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Amoxycillin"
    },
    {
      "question": "Everyone benefits from family planning except",
      "options": [
        "The mother",
        "The children",
        "The community member",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "None of the above"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Nigeria, composition of primary health care team include but not limited to these except",
      "options": [
        "Village health Workers",
        "JCHEW and CHEW Health workers",
        "Pharmacists and pharmacy technicians",
        "Traditional suit sayers and healers"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Traditional suit sayers and healers"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following is wrong in PHC",
      "options": [
        "Cases that could not be handled in secondary level are transferred to primary care level",
        "Cases that could not be handled in secondary levels are transferred to tertiary levels",
        "Cases that are difficult could be transferred to the secondary levels or tertiary levels",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Cases that could not be handled in secondary level are transferred to primary care level"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of the following disease has mostly decimated Nigerians",
      "options": ["HIV/AIDS", "Hypertension", "Malaria", "Diabetes"],
      "correctAnswer": "HIV/AIDS"
    },
    {
      "question": "The following are signs and symptoms of malaria except",
      "options": ["Fever", "Headaches", "Breathing with exertion", "Tiredness"],
      "correctAnswer": "Breathing with exertion"
    },
    {
      "question": "Chloroquine is no longer effective in the treatment of malaria because of",
      "options": [
        "High recurrence",
        "High resistance",
        "High re infection",
        "High prevalence"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "High resistance"
    },
    {
      "question": "………… has no cure presently",
      "options": ["HIV/AIDS", "Malaria", "Arthritis", "Typhoid fever"],
      "correctAnswer": "HIV/AIDS"
    },
    {
      "question": "The surest and most single habit to avoid HIV is",
      "options": [
        "Abstinence",
        "Using condom",
        "Be faithful to a sexual partner",
        "Avoid sharing unsterilized instrument"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Abstinence"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these STDs is nearly impossible to treat and incurable",
      "options": ["Genital herpes", "Syphilis", "Gonorrhea", "Genital wart"],
      "correctAnswer": "Genital herpes"
    },
    {
      "question": "Implantation of the embryo takes place at where?",
      "options": ["Uterus", "Fallopian tube", "Ovary", "Vulva"],
      "correctAnswer": "Uterus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Painful menstruation is called",
      "options": [
        "Amenorrhea",
        "Dysmenorrhea",
        "Menorrhagia",
        "Oligomenorrhea"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Dysmenorrhea"
    },
    {
      "question": "A woman who has not given birth to a child is called",
      "options": ["Primigravida", "Nullipara", "Multipara", "Gravid uterus"],
      "correctAnswer": "Nullipara"
    },
    {
      "question": "A woman who is carrying pregnancy for the first time is referred to as",
      "options": ["Primigravida", "Multipara", "Nullipara", "Multigravida"],
      "correctAnswer": "Primigravida"
    },
    {
      "question": "Most private hospitals are at which level of health care",
      "options": ["Tertiary", "Secondary", "Primary", "All of the above"],
      "correctAnswer": "Secondary"
    },
    {
      "question": "Health education encompasses all the following except",
      "options": [
        "Financial health",
        "Physical health",
        "Social health",
        "Emotional health"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Financial health"
    },
    {
      "question": "Health education is important because of all the following but one",
      "options": [
        "It builds knowledge about health",
        "It builds awareness about physical, mental and emotional health",
        "It encourages physical approach to every problems",
        "It teaches how to prevent diseases and reduce risk behaviours"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "It encourages physical approach to every problems"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following best summarizes the ultimate goal and purpose of health education",
      "options": [
        "To positively influence the health behavior of individuals and communities",
        "To encourage self reliance when it comes to personal hygiene",
        "To promote the health status and well being of individuals",
        "To encourage individuals to take charge and responsibility on matters that affect their health"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "To positively influence the health behavior of individuals and communities"
    },
    {
      "question": "Health communication seeks the following except",
      "options": [
        "Increase clients knowledge and awareness of a health issue",
        "Demonstrate health practices",
        "Advocate a position on a health issues or policy",
        "Decrease demand or support for health services"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Decrease demand or support for health services"
    },
    {
      "question": "Communication in health education is either",
      "options": [
        "Direct person to person or indirect",
        "Must be exclusively direct",
        "Must be indirect form of health communication",
        "Could be directly indirect"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Direct person to person or indirect"
    },
    {
      "question": "Posters when used to convey health information can be described as",
      "options": [
        "Direct and indirect form of communication",
        "Direct form of communication",
        "Indirect form of communication",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Indirect form of communication"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is true of a direct form of health communication",
      "options": [
        "The clients are usually the principal communicator",
        "The health worker is usually the principal communicator",
        "The audience are usually the principal communicator",
        "All of the above"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "The health worker is usually the principal communicator"
    },
    {
      "question": "VCT on HIV/AIDS means",
      "options": [
        "Voluntary counseling and testing",
        "Voluntarily conducted tests",
        "Volunteers on conducting tests",
        "None of the above"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Voluntary counseling and testing"
    },
    {
      "question": "ICCM means",
      "options": [
        "International committee on cases management",
        "International community case management",
        "Interaction on continue case management",
        "Integrated community case management"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Integrated community case management"
    },
    {
      "question": "The word ‘Alma- Ata’ as being commonly used in PHC means",
      "options": [
        "National conference on PHC",
        "Nigerian conference on PHC",
        "International conference on PHC",
        "State conference on PHC"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "International conference on PHC"
    },
    {
      "question": "The ‘Alma- Ata’ declaration of …………… emerged as a major milestone of the twentieth century in the field of public health",
      "options": ["1960", "1990", "1978", "2000"],
      "correctAnswer": "1978"
    },
    {
      "question": "The apex of the Nigerian health system is",
      "options": [
        "Teaching hospitals",
        "Specialist hospitals",
        "General hospitals",
        "Primary health centres"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Teaching hospitals"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is at the bottom level in health services in Nigeria?",
      "options": [
        "Health education",
        "Health insurance",
        "Primary health care services",
        "Secondary level health services"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Primary health care services"
    },
    {
      "question": "Skills for effective communication in health include all but one",
      "options": ["Convincing", "Observing", "Instructing", "Listening"],
      "correctAnswer": "Convincing"
    },
    {
      "question": "A process through which health care professionals attempt to increase patient knowledge and education on health care issues is called",
      "options": [
        "Patient convincing",
        "Patient care",
        "Patient information",
        "Patient counseling"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Patient counseling"
    },
    {
      "question": "Patient counseling methods involve all but one",
      "options": [
        "Introduction of the session",
        "Content of the session",
        "Voluminous process followed",
        "Conclusion of the session"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Voluminous process followed"
    },
    {
      "question": "Patient counseling can be concluded by all except;",
      "options": [
        "Not verifying patient understanding via feedback",
        "Summaries by acknowledging or emphasizing key points",
        "Provide an opportunity for final concerns or questions",
        "Help the patient to plan and follow up on next steps"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Not verifying patient understanding via feedback"
    },
    {
      "question": "Non verbal communication include all these except;",
      "options": ["Talking", "Facial expression", "Body postures", "Gestures"],
      "correctAnswer": "Talking"
    },
    {
      "question": "Essential amino acids include the following except",
      "options": ["Histidine", "Isoleucine", "Leucine", "None of the above"],
      "correctAnswer": "None of the above"
    },
    {
      "question": "Carbohydrates contains the elements",
      "options": ["Carbon", "Hydrogen", "Oxygen", "All of the above"],
      "correctAnswer": "All of the above"
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of the following is commonly abused drug",
      "options": ["Diclofenac", "Ibuprofen", "Tramadol", "Piroxicam"],
      "correctAnswer": "Tramadol"
    },
    {
      "question": "The organs of government with the sole authority of regularising and controlling of pharmacy technician programmes in Nigeria is",
      "options": ["NAFDAC", "NDLEA", "PCN", "PSN"],
      "correctAnswer": "PCN"
    },
    {
      "question": "Signs of pregnancy may include the following except",
      "options": [
        "Mood changes",
        "Breast tenderness",
        "Nausea and vomiting",
        "Convulsion"
      ],
      "correctAnswer": "Convulsion"
    },
    {
      "question": "Contraceptives product that are commonly being abused is",
      "options": ["Postinor", "Combination-3", "Mestrogen", "Post-pill"],
      "correctAnswer": "Postinor"
    }
  ]
}
